Danilo Orescanin speeches, 1983-1987 C226
Indiana University Archives
Danilo Orescanin speeches
1983-1987
Indiana University Archives
Orescanin, Danilo
C226
.2 cubic feet
Danilo Orescanin was a long time administrator associated with Indiana University in a variety of administrative roles. This collection contains speech files from his time as Vice President for University Relations between 1983 and 1987.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Advance notice is required.
Biographical
Danilo Orescanin served Indiana University in a number of different capacities during his career, most notably as Chancellor of the Northwest campus and subsequently as Vice President for University Relations. In both positions, he spoke frequently to university and community groups, and worked to strengthen I.U.'s relationship with the community at large.
Orescanin was born 7 April 1932 in Mingo Junction, Ohio, to George and Nellie (Kukich) Orescanin; his father had come to the United States from Serbia at the age of nineteen. Orescanin earned a bachelor's degree in business administration from West Virginia University in 1953 and an M.B.A. from Indiana University in 1954. He became an industrial engineer at Colgate-Palmolive in Jeffersonville, Indiana; was drafted into the army, in which he served in 1955 and 1956; and returned to I.U. to pursue a doctorate in business in 1957. By the time he received his doctorate in 1960, he had already had a taste of administrative work, having served as administrative assistant to the Dean of the School of Business.
Orescanin became an Assistant Professor of Business at the University of South Florida in Tampa in 1960, where he also served as Assistant Coordinator of Evening and Summer Sessions. In 1963 he returned to Indiana University as Assistant Dean of the Division of University Extension. Over the next nine years, he performed a variety of administrative functions for the University and held appointments first as an assistant and then as an associate professor of business. He was acting director of the Southeast campus from April to August of 1965, following the sudden death of Dr. Byron K. Laird. In the fall of 1965, Orescanin went to Dacca, Pakistan to establish a new graduate program at the Institute of Business Administration, Dacca University, serving as Resident Advisor until 1967. He returned to I.U. and served first as Assistant Dean and later Associate Dean of Research of Advanced Studies, meanwhile serving as Acting Director of Data Systems and Services. In 1969, he was appointed Assistant to President Joseph L. Sutton and Associate Dean for Administration, and continued as Assistant to President John W. Ryan until he was invited to follow David R. Derge to Southern Illinois University following the latter's appointment as president there early in 1972.
Orescanin served as Derge's executive assistant at S.I.U. from February to July of 1972, when he became Vice President for Administration and Campus Treasurer. Between July 1973 and March 1974, he also held the position of Executive Vice President. However, in late February 1974, Orescanin called Derge's attention to procedural irregularities in the use of some $5,000 from the Southern Illinois University Foundation to buy alcohol for presidential functions. As the accounts were under his control, Orescanin resigned from his administrative duties and requested reassignment to a full-time teaching and research position in the business school, which Derge granted. Orescanin was charged with tampering with public records by a grand jury of Jackson County, Illinois, but was acquitted.
Orescanin served as Chancellor of Indiana University Northwest from the fall semester of 1975 until June of 1983, during which time he worked to improve the financial and physical state of the campus and to improve the image of the campus in the surrounding communities. He was involved in a large number of community organizations, and was awarded a National Award for outstanding contributions and service by the Association of Teacher Educators in 1979, the first time the award was ever given to a non-education faculty member.
In June 1983, Orescanin was appointed Vice President for University Relations, a position that had been vacant for nearly three years. In this capacity, he oversaw the News Bureau, and the offices of University Publications, Community Relations, and Special Events, as well as the offices of University Relations at all campuses. He expanded the staff, which had been reduced in size, and implemented programs intended to create a strong statewide image for I. U. He showed a special interest in communities that had not previously had a strong I. U. presence such as "the Batesvilles, the Lawrenceburgs, the Evansvilles, and the Terre Hautes," as one article put it (Heck, The Columbian, Nov. 1983). He also launched a "Speakers Team" project to invite faculty members with the needed expertise speak to community groups around the state that might have questions about a particular field. His public relations style tended to emphasize personal connections: he compiled a list of "Friends of Indiana" in a wide range of counties and occupations for University Relations use, and sponsored golf events to build ties between members of the administration and influential people outside I. U., such as the news media. He served in the position of Vice President until January 1, 1988, when he returned to teaching management and business policy classes in the business school. In 1992, he was given the Otteson Undergraduate Teaching Excellence Award. He retired in December 1992, and died 22 May 1999 at the age of 67 in Tampa, Florida. Orescanin and his wife, Kathleen, had a son, Danilo II, and a daughter, Lori, both of whom earned degrees from I.U.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into one series, Vice Presidential Speeches. They are arranged chronologically.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of speeches given by Danilo Orescanin during his tenure as Vice President for University Relations; the material is arranged chronologically. The speeches were given to a variety of university and community organizations; roughly one-third were given to organizations such as Rotary and Kiwanis clubs, and another third at university functions or to university-affiliated groups. The collection also includes two speeches Orescanin gave at the Pro Football Hall of Fame. Most of the speeches are polished drafts, while a few are typewritten outlines.
Separated Material
Newsletter articles removed to clippings file, material relating to John W. Ryan removed to his clippings file.
Related Material
See also Collection C225, Danilo Orescanin speeches. These are speech files from Orscanin's term as Chancellor of the Indiana University Northwest campus between 1976 and 1983.
Acquisition Information
Accession 8221.
College orations --Indiana University.; College administrators --Indiana --Bloomington --Speeches.; College administrators --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Orescanin, Danilo -- Speeches; Orescanin, Danilo -- Speeches -- Selections; Indiana University. Vice-President for University Relations -- Archives; Indiana University. Vice-President for University Relations -- Speeches; Indiana University. Office of University Relations -- Archives; Indiana University. Office of University Relations -- History -- 20th century -- Sources
- Vice Presidential speeches, 1983-1987
  - United Way Luncheon, 12 Sep 1983 (Box 1)
  - Student Organizations Forum, 1 Oct 1983 (Box 1)
  - Indiana Academy of Sciences, 7 Oct 1983 (Box 1)
  - Pro Football Hall of Fame, 31 Oct 1983 (Box 1)
  - Monroe County Education Association Banquet, 16 Nov 1983 (Box 1)
  - Saint Sava Parish (Serbian Church), 20 Nov 1983 (Box 1)
  - Remarks to Rotary Club (Seymour), 21 Nov 1983 (Box 1)
  - Bloomington Press Club, 16 Dec 1983 (Box 1)
  - Northwestern Indiana Regional Planning Commission Annual Meeting, 19 Jan 1984 (Box 1)
  - Columbus, Ind. Rotary Club, 1984 Jun 11 (Box 1)
  - Welcoming Remarks—High School Science Institute, 12 Aug 1984 (Box 1)
  - Clevenger Award Ceremony, 27 Oct 1984 (Box 1)
  - Jasper Kiwanis Club, 22 Jan 1985 (Box 1)
  - Indiana Business Leaders' Meeting, 23 Jan 1985 (Box 1)
  - Dedication, Purdue University Engineering-Technology Program, 31 Jan 1985 (Box 1)
  - Kiwanis Club (Petersburg), 13 Mar 1985 (Box 1)
  - Founders Day--Cass & Carroll Counties, 19 Mar 1985 (Box 1)
  - Bloomington Downtown Kiwanis Club, 27 Jun 1985 (Box 1)
  - Indianapolis Public Relations Society, 18 Sep 1985 (Box 1)
  - Bloomington Northside Rotary Club, 23 Jan 1986 (Box 1)
  - Student Lecture Series, 12 Feb 1986 (Box 1)
  - I. U. Foundation, 28 Feb 1986 (Box 1)
  - Symposium on Japan, 3 Apr 1986 (Box 1)
  - IUSA Dinner, 13 Apr 1986 (Box 1)
  - Kiwanis Club (Evansville), 17 Apr 1986 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Executive Council Luncheon, 13 Jun 1986 (Box 1)
  - Pro Football Hall of Fame, 3 Nov 1986 (Box 1)
  - ROTC Review, 15 Apr 1987 (Box 1)